[SPEAKER_00]: But then, based on our yesterday's discussion, I was thinking that, peripherally by talking about, can it be understood as the field on which the particular manifests?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes and no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, in a sense that, yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: A particular, they arise on the basis
[SPEAKER_01]: of that more general or more peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the sense bases, for example, are referred to as... can be translated as fields, with the same... in the same sense, actually, because the sense objects that arise on a particular level, they arise on the basis of the field of the eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I said that that's why it's yes, but it can be answered no, if you give that field some sort of priority over the particulars, because that field is a negative phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's defined by the things that arise particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can discern that there is a field because the I-objects are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the particular things have a reason, the peripheral is generated because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's defined because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not independent of the particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, the question you ask is valid, but sometimes it can be asked in a sense of which is first, which is more important, which is greater.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in that sense, I have to be careful how to answer, because then people will just think, ah, okay, so there's this field, and then things arise upon the field, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think like that, you're taking that field to be the particular, which means something else is then peripheral in regard to that thought of that very defined field.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's one thing to understand the level of your mind, sort of thinking, intellectually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's important to clarify as much as you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, if you want to recognize it as the actual phenomena that which that field is, that is always generated on the basis of the current particulars.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you start.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're just mindful of the present situation of the body and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, based on that, this is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just need to discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, recognize that which you have intellectually grasped beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you have, sort of, the information and the data to... to, sort of, eh... identify.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you have, nāmarūpa determines viññāṇa in as much as viññāṇa determines nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two sticks holding each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is not more than the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one cannot even be conceived without the other being simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how, by full understanding that, there is absolutely no room for the sense of self, for the appropriation to remain there, because it becomes completely redundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole picture...
[SPEAKER_01]: These two sticks, they don't need any master operator.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, they support each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as the five aggregates are present, things will be arising and manifesting and defining itself, defining the... and everything else will continue operating, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: The intention, the volition, all that would stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what wouldn't stay is the owner of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's no room for the owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: The owner is part of that stick.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what can you own?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you own the left stick?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's being supported by the right one, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, well, I might think I own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the right stick goes, the left one cannot stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you own the right stick, if it's being held by the left one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't hold them both at the same time, because that will imply you stepping outside of your experience and then taking up the hold of its foundations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the practice, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the vipassana, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that repetition or that contemplation
[SPEAKER_01]: of this, uh, mutual dependence of these things whereby, by fully discerning that, you automatically squeeze out any sense of appropriation itself, because it's just inconceivable to be there at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes redundant, completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you use the approach of saḷāyātana, the sense bases, yes, they're the negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're the base.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're the field.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think the old translations of Jnana-mūlitera, the first, was the...
[SPEAKER_01]: He was certainly experimenting with it at some point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a field.
[SPEAKER_01]: A field.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think Navid was as well referring to it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because, like, from yesterday, when I was meditating,
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually realized that it seems that all these saḷāyātanas are all the time operating, and your attention just picked up one small piece, one moment, from that whole, you know, inconceivable amount of possibilities, and you actually have no idea what will come in the next
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you have a very limited idea, and that limit is given to you by the thing beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you're not in control even of that idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just come, like, afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is already set up, and you just come on the scene.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The six sense bases
[SPEAKER_01]: These six fields of possibilities, these six negatives, six peripherals, if that's the approach you take, eh... yeah, they're simultaneously present there all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your attention obviously arises on the basis of one particular among them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Veda, I thought, whatever takes... takes your fancy or presses you the hardest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And can you explain what keeps the negative
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the narrative is kept by the mind, because the five senses meet in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind does, for its own object, has the overview of the five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how they are intelligible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you have a... Putujana has an extra layer of narrative, which is his ātrāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: And his sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That adds a whole another assumed dimension of another point of view that's external to all of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the mind, that's just arahant as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he he has a narrative, he has a context, he he can still operate and talk and discern and choose and prefer, because the mind is where the senses meet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the mind cannot be overwhelmed by the senses anymore, so nothing that he chooses or prefers will be based on anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for Putrajana, he has assumed another completely gratuitous dimension of his sense of self being independent of both that mind and all those senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just completely outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's holding both of the sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the idea of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the notion of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the meaning of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see how much more complex than the narrative becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And much more unpredictable as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly... that's exactly why, like, having the sense of self results in suffering, results... because you're trying... you're sort of acting as if you are the center of experience, yet, like, every single experience you have, that is being undermined through the very experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why if a patujana would stop engaging in the world, stop engaging in the desires, practicing restraint, go and close himself in a little cell, in a little room, first it would be the boredom that would come, and then it would be a sheer dread and fear, and many people would lose their minds.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is nothing, nothing taking away that... Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they remain holding.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot not hold to their sense of self, to that assumed external entity, really, that is just being now crushed from every possible conceivable direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he recognizes the prospect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He feels it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so terrifying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why when the quotidian would talk to the Buddha sometimes, and he would tell what he teaches, they would understand what he... they would understand the dispassion, the point, the view of nibbāna, like abandoning it all before it's taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they wouldn't let go of their sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that understanding would completely make them go mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would fall on the ground, pull their hair, beat their breast.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, full-on panic attack and dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they don't let go of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they understood clearly that all these things, they come to an end, that self owns.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet,
[SPEAKER_01]: If the self owns, means self will be owning its ending as well, the ending of those things, but it can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize the self will be destroyed, and then they would lament and say, well, that will destroy us, that will kill us.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be nothing left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in their mind it's the self that sort of governs all of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems that this approach can really disentangle that notion of start, because if you realize how broad everything is, that it's not just your particular experience, but there is that whole thing around, which you can't control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably it's a bad word.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what you mean, but it probably means it will extinguish.
[SPEAKER_01]: That dimension that is being gratuitously maintained and generated as the external dimension to the whole experience, which is where the self abides and lives as the master, as the god.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start noticing that that dimension, it's already peripheral, that has peripheral to it, you realize there is no outside to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you think outside, that's the experience inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even your thoughts of external are experienced right here, right now, internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can't step outside of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not hard to grasp on the intellectual level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It kind of makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Willing it long enough until the mind stops, sort of, wavering and going out of it, even with those kind of careless, lazy, sort of, thinking assumptions, that will take time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the more you do it, the more, sort of, you're kind of, well, as I said, you're sort of fading away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That notion of external dimension, because no matter what external dimension you're thinking presently, right now, mindfully, you realize that's already surrounded by its own peripheral, which means it cannot be the ultimate external, which means it cannot be the ultimate owner, the ultimate self, the ultimate God, the ultimate anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all a reason on the basis of the particular experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, yeah, that was the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was just that little kind of careless, careless way of attending to things, assuming the external to yourself, to your experience, to others, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just that was enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was enough for this whole mess of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why ignorance and wrong view is the most blameworthy thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, that's why careless attention is in the beginning of the whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why if somebody, somebody just sort of stops gradually, fades away, the assuming of that external dimension, he basically stops assuming the Atavāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what Atavāda is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he becomes free from the factor of the self-view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it so that yoniso manasikāra is actually in regards to these things we are talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yoniso manasikāra... yoniso means womb.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, the root, the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see, like, if the normal attention is the attention that's usually completely focused upon the object, and even if it steps away from the object into a more general picture, it makes that an object.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it always... the measure for ordinary yoniso manasikāra is the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't see anything simultaneously present that's peripheral to that attended object.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it starts to train itself to start noticing other things while it is still attending the present object, whatever that object is, whatever sense that might have been sort of most dominant, if it starts noticing those particular without making them into a new object, so you keep your old attention, so to speak, on the object, and simultaneously, while that is present, you start noticing other things that are there, simultaneously present, but not the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you start training the mind to discern other things different from that which you're used to discerning, which is only an object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the same attention, you start looking at the origins of that object.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's behind it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's around it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's higher than it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of the structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start looking at the structure of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start looking at the womb from which it all originated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like... people often translate proper attention improperly, or rather lazily and carelessly, whereby it just means like a... oh, it's a wholesome attention, just when you attend good and you think good.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more precise than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's such a fundamental aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one of the factors for the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Equally important as the word of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have all the words of the Buddha and all the Buddhas.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have no proper attention, none of that will make sense or take root.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, it's discerning the structure through the arisen thing, without sort of making it into a new thing, because then the structure is somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, that's how you train your attention to become proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it attends to whatever attends, but it sees beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't get locked onto just the face value of the arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I still feel that there is actually a danger that instead of, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, seeing the structure, you just step back and you only broaden... Well, it has to start like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it has to start like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as long as you know that you'll be supposed to be seeing the peripheral in regard to whatever, it starts in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you step back, you broaden the experience, but then that becomes particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, through that, you keep discerning further.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there is no end to it, it's infinite, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can keep doing that as much as you like.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the whole point of doing it is to start discerning that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Field and the thing that isn't upon the field, that defines field in its return.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, in some sense, you don't necessarily have to have kind of greatly developed mind to discern the principle of pratītyasamupāda, of that interdependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to, because you can discern the principle upon very basic things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you discern the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is this, there is that.
[SPEAKER_00]: This.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this is present, this is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there is a field...
[SPEAKER_01]: For things to be sort of arisen upon, things arise upon it, which in return define that field as that which they're not at the time they have arisen upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's fully mutually determining each other, and you realize that's how everything works in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, in a way, Bhaktisiddhānta Mahāprabhu explains how everything works in a very direct, insightful manner, whereby if you understand it, you automatically stop regarding things as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're automatically free from yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're... basically, if you... if you fully develop it, you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't explain it in a sense of telling you what's happening, and it provides as an explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It kind of requires time, and it's sort of linear, and succession of things, and when this changes, and this goes, and then... and then, oh, yeah, they really... that's really... they really... they really make sense, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more precise than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's not necessarily wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it is, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is wrong in a sense that... but this, somehow, should be taken as a precise thing, because then people will take it seriously, and... and then try to discern this very thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's very, very hard to discern, as you can see for yourself now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're starting to get the idea what it refers to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually discerning it, and then discerning this relationship, it's just the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everybody, somebody starts with this, this is, and then with what, what is, and then it carries on into twelve factors, or sixteen factors, or eight factors, depending how the Buddha describes it on different occasions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same, it's the same principle that's being described.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see what kind of understanding would be required to see that principle in all those intricate
[SPEAKER_01]: ways of relating to each other, as the Buddha would have described, that it's a part of the birth and everything else, as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, the good news is, you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have to do is see the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is basically nothing else than saying, oh, yes, whatever has arisen, for that reason, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, I understand, basically, if you really see the principle, then you abolish or extinguish that notion of right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it was said in the suttas, Sariputra said,
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, or the Buddha, the one who sees the... Sariputra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sariputra said, the one who sees dhamma, sees paticca upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one who sees paticca upādāna, sees the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, also, it must be as important as any other, kind of, directly relevant aspect of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is, there's so much, obviously, wrong notions, explanations, views, based upon paticca upādāna today.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's probably even better if people don't bother with it, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to figure it out, because it's... because there's so much out, it's quite likely they'll be pulled to one wrong side or the other and end up doing it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... it's not necessarily crucial or a deal-breaker.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a person still remains authentic and knows why they're practicing and what... what's supposed to sort of be uprooted with the understanding, they'll... they'll figure it out eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really not necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just understand the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't worry about the twelve, or eight, or sixteen, whichever way the world is, probably, don't worry about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just understand the two sticks supporting each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just understand peripheral and actual, actual peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because fully understanding it will leave no room for the sense of self to be assumed at.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: The self was never there, as you can see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, by not knowing that it's there...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the presence of not-knowledge, of non-knowledge, that self cannot be there, the presence of that phenomena places the self there to the extent of that phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your non-knowledge that self cannot be there was great, quite sort of spread around your experience, your self is to the same extent spread about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're fully responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, consequently, fully understood, fully removing the non-knowledge, replacing with knowledge that self cannot be anywhere there, the self is not anywhere there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why there is the element of nibbāna in Putujana's experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nothing other than saying there's a possibility of him to achieve nibbāna, to free himself from himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is possible because the structure can never be actually penetrated or affected by the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were, that means the self would have some input.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be a sort of a master.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until you know that, then it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it was said upādāna is not the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not all of them, not even one of them, not even the bits of them, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no upādāna without them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same self, in the same sense, the self is in regard to the experience as a whole, but it's not actually there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, for Pratyujana, who doesn't question that self, he assumes it elsewhere, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: external to the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you take that away, then he realizes, well, it cannot be elsewhere, so it can't hide there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly, it can't fit in here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it fades.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're left with no choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why you kind of indirectly, you keep shutting down the escape, the escape routes for the assumption of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't directly stop assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you know, wait a minute, the vision needs to be unscrewed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just knock it out as a trick.